Guide to the Robert E. Upson Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robert E. Upson family papers
1816-1989
1816-1882
MS 1578
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.75
(3 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence and business, legal, and financial papers which document the life of Ashahel Upson, a farmer and tinsmith in Southington, Connecticut. The papers also trace the settlement and business ventures of Upson's nine sons in Alabama, Kansas, California, and Montana.
Upson family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Helen R. Upson, 1989.
Scope and Contents
The Robert E. Upson Papers consist of correspondence and business, legal, and financial papers, which document the lives of Ashahel Upson and his nine sons. The elder Upson owned a farm and tin shop in Southington, Connecticut. The papers include accounts of the farm and shop as well as the sale of tin goods by members of the Langdon family. Through correspondence and financial records, the papers trace the careers of the Upson children, several of whom settled in the South and California. The papers also record business ventures by family members in Kansas and Montana. The Odyssey of a Connecticut Family in Pursuit of the American Dream, a history of the Upson family, is also included in the papers. Helen Rena Upson, the author of this study, donated the papers to the Manuscripts and Archives Department in 1989; the papers are named in honor of her father.
Appendix
Robert E. Upson Family
Asahel Upson (1783-1867) m. (1806) Lydia Webster
Asahel Lauren (1807-1885) m. Selina Chatfield
Asahel Warren (1807-1835)
Asahel James Robert (1809-1877) m. (1859) Mary Jones
Asahel DeWitt (1812-1879) m. Harriet Smith
Asahel Edwin (b.1814) m. Priscilla Maxwell (d. 1855)
Asahel Augustus (b. 1816) m. (1849) Dorinda Weeks (d. 1854)
Asahel Augustus (b. 1816) m. (1860) Maria A. Gray
Asahel Josiah (1818-1856) m. Dolly
Asahel Charles (1821-1885) m. (1852) Sophia Upham
Asahel Gad Ely (1823-1866) m. Lucy Langdon (b.1833)
Biographical / Historical
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Upson family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Families; Tin industry -- Connecticut; Alabama -- Commerce; California -- Commerce; Connecticut -- Commerce; Montana -- Commerce; Southington (Conn.); Account books; Merchants; Upson, James R.; Langston family; Upson family
- Correspondence, 1820s, 1840s, 1850s, 1860s (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
- Business, legal and financial papers
  - Account book of Levi Langdon, 1816-1835 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Account book of Perry Langdon, 1823-1850 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Account book of the Perry Langdon store, 1830s-1860s (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Account book of Asahel Upson, 1826-1841, 1877 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Account book of James Upson, 1854-1882 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Upson & Company, El Dorado County, California, 1852-1858 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Bradley Manufacturing & Trading Company, Marion, Connecticut, 1854 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Suit of Chester Case and Samuel Wilson v. Lauren and James R. Upson in Litchfield Superior Court, 1855 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Quindaro, Kansas property, 1857-1858 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Montana business, 1865-1868 (Box 3, Folder 14-18)
  - Estate of Gad Upson, 1868-1869 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Sermon by Josiah Upson, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- The Odyssey of a Connecticut Family in Pursuit of the American Dream, by Helen Rena Upson, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 21)